Guide to the J. Walter Thompson Company. John F. Devine Papers, 1952-1974 and undated, bulk 1956-1970 RL.00683
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Radio/Television Department Series, 1952-1963 and undated
  - Client Subseries, 1952-1963 and undated
    - 1963
      - Dean Witter (Box 16)
      - Kraft Foods, a division of National Dairy Products Corporation, 4 folders
        - General, 2 folders (Box 16)
        - Perry Como-Kraft Music Hall (Box 16)
        - Television productions, 1963 and undated (Box 16)
      - Pitney-Bowes (Box 16)
  - Programming Subseries, 1955-1960 and undated
    Comprises correspondence, memoranda, questionnaires, reports, telexes, telegrams, charts, and verifaxes illustrating proposed programming concepts, the availability of actors and actresses, and the evolution of television production facilities. Also includes materials relating to Chicago, Hollywood, and New York operations; production of local programming in New York; as well as the house production facility in New York City, known as TV Workshop. Some materials have been relocated to Oversize Materials. Arranged alphabetically.
    - Availabilities, 1955-1960 and undated, 6 folders (Box 16)
    - Chicago office (Box 17)
      - General, 1955-1958 and undated (Box 17)
      - Television program availabilities, 1957 (Box 17)
    - Client sponsored programs for 1958, 1958 and undated (Box 17)
    - General, 1955-1960 and undated (Box 17)
    - Hollywood office, 7 folders
      - Office files, 1956-1958 and undated, 2 folders (Box 17)
      - Office organization, 1955-1956 and undated (Box 17)
      - Screening and availability reports, 1955-1960 and undated, 4 folders (Box 17)
    - New York office, 10 folders (Box 18)
      - Local television production, 1956-1960 and undated (Box 18)
      - Publicity and program exploitation, 1956-1958 and undated, 3 folders (Box 18)
      - Traffic, 1956-1958 and undated (Box 18)
      - Television art department, 1956-1958 and undated (Box 18)
      - Television commercial production, 1956-1960 and undated (Box 18)
      - TV Workshop, 1955-1960 and undated, 3 folders (Box 18)
    - Screening reports, 1955-1956 and undated (Box 19)
    - Talent showcase, 1955-1956 and undated (Box 19)
  - Research Subseries, 1956-1960 and undated
    Includes correspondence, memoranda, questionnaires, reports, telexes, telegrams, charts, and verifaxes documenting the introduction of formal consumer research into the advertising industry. Shows the development of increasingly sophisticated research services to analyze discrete market groups, project audience reaction to different types of commercial appeals, and to adapt materials to persuade consumers to purchase certain products. Additional materials related to research for specific clients are located in the Office Files Subseries of the Corporate Administration Series (Restricted). Some materials moved to Oversize Materials. Arranged alphabetically by topic.
    - American Association of Advertising Agencies (4As), TV-Radio Creative Workshop, 1956 and undated (Box 19)
    - A. C. Nielsen ratings, 1956-1958 and undated, 3 folders (Box 19)
    - Consumer Panel, 1956-1958 and undated (Box 19)
    - Methodology and studies, 1954-1960 and undated, 3 folders (Box 19)
    - Ratings, 1956-1958 and undated, 2 folders (Box 20)
  - Talent Negotiations Subseries 1953-1960, and undated
    Comprises correspondence, memoranda, reports, telexes, telegrams, charts, and verifaxes evidencing the concerns of advertising agencies, advertisers, and labor representatives regarding the contractual control, practices, and payment of performers and radio and television support personnel. In addition to his employment with JWT, Devine served as an appointed advertising industry representative in negotiations with various unions, particularly the negotiation of the 1958 contract with Screen Actors Guild (SAG). The correspondence, memoranda, and reports in this subseries document the inception and growth of organized labor movements such as the American Federation of Musicians (AFM), American Federation of Radio and Television Artists (AFTRA), American Society of Composers, Authors, and Publishers (ASCAP), Screen Actors Guild (SAG), and Writers Guild of America (WGA) in representing performers and support personnel in radio and television programming. Organized labor significantly affected the business procedures and economic practices of the advertising industry. Arranged alphabetically by topic.
    - American Association of Advertising Agencies (4As)-Standing Committee on Television and Radio Administration, 1956-1960 and undated, 4 folders (Box 20)
    - American Federation of Musicians (AFM), 1958 and undated (Box 20)
    - American Federation of Television and Radio Artists (AFTRA), 1958-1960 and undated, 3 folders (Box 21)
    - American Society of Composers, Authors, and Publishers (ASCAP), 1958 (Box 21)
    - Client talent issues, 1953-1960 and undated (Box 21)
    - National Labor Relations Board (NLRB), 1958 and undated, 2 folders (Box 21)
    - Screen Actors Guild (SAG), 2 folders
      - General, 1958 and undated (Box 21)
      - Negotiation of 1958 contract, 1958 and undated (Box 21)
    - Writers Guild of America (WGA), 1958 (Box 21)
  - Television Networks Subseries, 1955-1960 and undated
    Includes correspondence, charts, rate cards, reports, and programming structures developed by the three networks--American Broadcasting Company (ABC), Columbia Broadcasting System (CBS), and National Broadcasting Company (NBC)--and the advertising industry. Demonstrates the growing influence of the networks in relation to the financial terms and organizational structure of television programs and commercials. Arranged alphabetically by topic.
    - American Broadcasting Company (ABC), 1956-1960 and undated (Box 22)
    - Columbia Broadcasting System (CBS), 1955-1960 and undated, 2 folders (Box 22)
    - Federal Communications Commission (FCC) Network Study, 1958 and undated (Box 22)
    - General, 1955-1960 and undated (Box 22)
    - National Broadcasting Company (NBC), 1956-1960 and undated (Box 22)
- Corporate Administration Series, 1953-1974 and undated (Restricted)
  Includes correspondence, memoranda, reports, charts, tables, telexes, telegrams, and verifaxes created or used by Devine as part of his corporate administrative duties regardless of where in JWT he was working at the time. Although the series includes some materials from Devine's early years as the Radio/Television Department administrator, the more significant files arise from Devine's activities as a corporate executive in New York from 1960 to 1970. In contrast to the Radio/Television Department Series, the bulk of this series relates to larger corporate issues rather than to specific client matters. Devine was particularly adept as a financial manager on the corporate level as indicated in his detailed personal charts and notes. Organized into five subseries: Committees/Groups, Correspondence, Office Files, Offices, and Review Board. Arranged alphabetically within each series. Some materials relocated to Oversize Materials.
  - Committees/Groups Subseries, 1954-1970 and undated
    Includes correspondence, memoranda, and reports from different committees or groups within JWT in which Devine participated. The largest amount of materials relate to the activities of the New York Operations Committee from 1960 to 1963. Some materials relocated to Oversize Materials. Arranged alphabetically by topic.
    - Committee of Representatives, 1960-1961 and undated (Box 22)
    - Communications Committee, 1956-1958 and undated (Box 22)
    - Finance Committee, 1963-1965 and undated, 3 folders (Box 22)
    - Fiscal Group, 1955-1958 and undated (Box 22)
    - Group 8, 1962-1967 and undated (Box 22)
    - Junior Management Luncheon Group, 1954-1955 (Box 22)
    - Management Committee, 1956 and undated (Box 22)
    - Meeting Club, 1966-1970 and undated (Box 23)
    - Monday Morning Group, 1955-1956 and undated (Box 23)
    - New York Operations Committee, 1960-1963 and undated, 5 folders (Box 23)
    - Staff Development Committee, 1956 (Box 23)
    - Wednesday Group (Production control group), 1956-1958 (Box 23)
  - Correspondence Subseries, 1954-1961 and undated
    Includes correspondence, memoranda, reports, charts, telegrams, and notes from Devine's tenure as the Radio/Television Department administrator. A portion of Devine's correspondence for the years 1954, 1958, and 1961 was found in chronological order with an index and retained in that order. Additional correspondence for those years and others may be found in the general correspondence and solicitation files. Arranged alphabetically.
    - Chronological, 1954-1961, folder 1 of 11 folders (Box 23)
    - Chronological, 1954-1961 (con't.), folders 2-10 of 11 folders (Box 24)
    - Chronological, 1954-1961 (con't.), folder 11 of 11 folders (Box 25)
    - General, 1956-1960, 3 folders (Box 25)
    - Solicitations, 1956-1960 (Box 25)
  - Office Files Subseries, 1961-1974 and undated
    Includes correspondence, memoranda, reports, charts, and notes from Devine's activities as a corporate executive between 1961 and 1974. Devine was particularly involved in efforts to reduce JWT cost expenditures and increase corporate profit, and there are numerous files relating to employee compensation, capital expenditures, financial analysis, and research requests (including information about the proposed research project, its purpose, methodology, costs, and expenses). Devine was one of the corporate officers with authority to approve research cost expenditures, and he retained a significant number of requests that he approved. Additional materials involving client research can also be found in the Research Subseries of the Corporate Administrative Series. Other topics include minority relations, both in employment of minorities by advertising agencies and participation of minorities in television programs and commercials. Additional materials involving JWT's efforts to comply with corporate and governmental regulation of minority employment and retention can also be found in the Detroit and Hollywood files in the Offices Subseries of the Corporate Administrative Series.
    - 1961
      - Breed, Abbott and Morgan-Corporate Counsel, 1961 and undated (Box 25)
      - Broadcast Advertisers Reports, Inc. (Box 25)
      - Corporate structure, 1961 and undated (Box 25)
      - Electronic data processing (computer processing), 1961 and undated (Box 25)
      - Employee transfer expense reimbursement, 1961 and undated (Box 25)
      - Expense authorizations, 1961 and undated (Box 25)
      - Federal Communications Commission (FCC), 1961 and undated (Box 25)
      - Federal Trade Commission (FTC) (Box 25)
      - Finance Dept., 1961 and undated, 2 folders (Box 25)
      - Industrial and Professional Dept. (Box 25)
      - Legal Dept., 1961 and undated, 2 folders
        - General (Box 25)
        - Meeting agendas (Box 25)
      - Marketing Research Dept., 1961 and undated (Box 26)
      - Media Dept., 1961 and undated (Box 26)
      - New product development, 1961 and undated (Box 26)
      - New York office, 1961 and undated (Box 26)
      - Salaries, 1961 and undated (Box 26)
      - Speeches (Box 26)
      - Spot Contracts, 1961 and undated (Box 26)
      - Taxes, 1959-1961 and undated (Box 26)
      - Traffic Dept., 1959-1962 and undated (Box 26)
      - United States Dept. of Navy security clearances (Box 26)
      - Western Union Telegraph Company claim (Box 26)
    - 1962
      - Ford Motor Company, 1961-1963 and undated (Box 26)
      - Lambert and Feasley-Advertising agency acquisition, 3 folders
        - Employee issues, 1962-1963 and undated (Box 26)
        - General, 1962-1963 and undated (Box 26)
        - Uris office lease, 1962 and undated (Box 26)
      - Marketing Research Dept., 1961-1963 and undated (Box 27)
      - New client strategies, 1962-1963 and undated (Box 27)
      - Norman H. Strouse, 6 folders
        - "Buff Papers," 1962-1963 (Box 27)
          Reprints of published articles that Strouse distributed to key management personnel and known as "buff papers" because of the beige paper on which they were printed.
        - General, 1962 and undated, 3 folders (Box 27)
        - Speeches
          - J. Walter Thompson executives, 1962-1963 and undated (Box 27)
          - Norman H. Strouse, 1962-1963 (Box 27)
      - Public Relations Dept., 1962 and undated (Box 28)
      - Research Dept., 3 folders
        - Analysis of 1961 costs and allocation, 1962 and undated (Box 28)
        - Cost Projections (Box 28)
        - General, 1962 and undated (Box 28)
      - Scott Paper Company (Box 28)
      - Traffic Dept., 1962-1963 and undated (Box 28)
    - 1963
      - Minority relations (Box 28)
    - 1964
      - Employee recruitment, 1964 and undated (Box 28)
      - European Managers Meeting, 1964 and undated, 2 folders (Box 28)
      - JWT 100th Anniversary, 1964 and undated (Box 28)
    - 1965
      - International managers meeting (February, March, and July), 1965 and undated, 2 folders (Box 28)
      - International managers meetings (March and July 1965), 1965 and undated (Box 28)
    - 1966
      - Financial expenditure comparisons, 1966-1968 and undated, 2 folders (Box 28)
    - 1967
      - Corporate titles (Box 29)
      - Pupil dialation project, 1967 and undated (Box 29)
      - Speech, E. G. Wilson, JWT-1966 and Beyond (Box 29)
    - 1968
      - Client listing 1886-1968 (Box 29)
      - Minority relations, 1964-1968 and undated, 2 folders (Box 29)
    - 1969
      - Capital expenditures, 1968-1970 and undated (Box 29)
      - Corporate policy notebook, 1962-1969 and undated (Box 29)
      - Dillon, Agnew and Marton, Inc., possible acquisition, 1969 and undated (Box 29)
      - Financial expenditure comparisons, 1969 and undated, 2 folders (Box 29)
      - New York office remodeling (Box 29)
      - Taxation, 1962-1969 and undated (Box 29)
    - 1970
      - Astronaut special, 1970 and undated (Box 30)
      - Digisonics teleproof system for coding commercials, 1970 and undated (Box 30)
      - Electronics and Alloys, Inc., 1967-1970 and undated (Box 30)
      - Financial expenditure comparisons, 1970-1971 and undated (Box 30)
      - Insurance, 1965-1970 and undated (Box 30)
      - Management consultants, 1968-1970 and undated (Box 30)
      - MPO Videotronics Inc., 1968-1971 and undated (Box 30)
      - New York office dining room, 1966-1970 and undated (Box 30)
      - Tipperary Land and Exploration Corp. (Box 30)
    - 1971
      - Advertising awards policy (Box 30)
      - Aspens Systems Corporation, 1968-1972 and undated (Box 30)
      - Employee loans, 1970-1971 and undated (Box 30)
      - Federal Trade Commission (FTC), 1971 and undated (Box 30)
      - Gillette Company Toni products, 1971 and undated (Box 30)
      - Investments, 1971 and undated (Box 30)
      - Long-term planning (Box 30)
      - Tassaway, Inc., 1971 and undated (Box 30)
    - 1972
      - Compensation study, 1971-1972 and undated (Box 30)
      - Data processing report (computer processing), 2 folders (Box 31)
      - Employee loans, 1972 and undated (Box 31)
      - Executive compensation study, 1972 and undated (Box 31)
      - Insurance, 1972 and undated (Box 31)
      - Salary budgets (Box 31)
      - Stock plan, 1971-1972 and undated (Box 31)
    - 1973
      - Employee loans, 1973 and undated (Box 31)
      - Investments (Box 31)
      - JWT Management Luncheon Program (Box 31)
    - 1974
      - Employee loans, 1974 and undated (Box 31)
      - Financial, 1973-1974 and undated (Box 31)
      - Insurance, 1974 and undated (Box 31)
      - Lord, Geller, Federico, Peterson agency acquisition, 1973-1974 and undated (Box 31)
      - Management bonus plan, 1970-1974 and undated, 2 folders (Box 31)
      - Salary budgets, 1973-1974 and undated (Box 31)
      - Stock incentive plan, 1971-1974 and undated (Box 31)
  - Offices Subseries, 1962-1974 and undated
    Comprises correspondence, memoranda, telegrams, reports, charts, architectural drawings, and notes relating to the operations of JWT offices, primarily in Canada, Chicago, and Hollywood. There is a significant amount of correspondence, memoranda, and reports focusing on the Montreal office and the difficulty of establishing and sustaining profitable accounts in Canada. In addition, minority relations, especially the employment and retention of minority employees in JWT offices, are documented in the Detroit and Hollywood Offices Files, particularly statistics recording JWT's efforts to comply with corporate and governmental regulation of minority employment and retention. Additional materials involving minority relations, both in employment of minorities by advertising agencies and participation of minorities in television programs and commercials, may be found in the Office Files Subseries of the Corporate Administration Series.
    - Canada (Box 32)
      - 1966
        - Budget, 1966 and undated (Box 32)
      - 1967
        - Budget, 1967 and undated (Box 32)
        - General, 1967 and undated, 2 folders (Box 32)
      - 1968
        - Budget, 1968 and undated, 2 folders (Box 32)
        - General, 1968 and undated (Box 32)
        - Montreal office relocation, 1967-1970 and undated (Box 32)
        - Pension plan, 1967-1968 and undated (Box 33)
      - 1969
        - Clients, 1969 and undated (Box 33)
        - Financial, 1969 and undated (Box 33)
        - General, 1969 and undated (Box 33)
        - Vancouver property (Box 33)
      - 1970
        - Financial, 1970 and undated (Box 33)
        - General, 1970 and undated (Box 33)
        - Insurance (Box 33)
        - New business, 1970 and undated (Box 33)
        - Public relations, 1970 and undated (Box 33)
    - Chicago
      - 1962
        - General, 1962-1963 and undated (Box 33)
        - Personnel administration changes for Chicago and Detroit offices, 1962 and undated (Box 33)
      - 1965
        - General, 1965-1966 and undated (Box 34)
      - 1967
        - General, 1967 and undated (Box 34)
      - 1968
        - Financial, 1968 and undated (Box 34)
        - General, 1968 and undated (Box 34)
      - 1969
        - General, 1969 and undated (Box 34)
        - John Hancock building move, 1968-1969 and undated, 2 folders (Box 34)
      - 1970
        - General, 1970 and undated (Box 34)
    - Detroit
      - 1962
        - General, 1962 and undated (Box 34)
      - 1973
        - Financial, 1973 and undated (Box 34)
        - General, 1973 and undated (Box 34)
      - 1974
        - Financial, 1974 and undated (Box 34)
        - General (Box 34)
    - Hollywood
      - 1962
        - General, 1962 and undated (Box 35)
      - 1963
        - General, 1963 and undated (Box 35)
      - 1966
        - General, 1966 and undated (Box 35)
      - 1967
        - General, 1967 and undated (Box 35)
      - 1968
        - Eastman Kodak-Richard Harris contract, 1968 and undated (Box 35)
        - General, 1958 and undated (Box 35)
      - 1969
        - General, 1969 and undated (Box 35)
      - 1970
        - General, 1970 and undated (Box 35)
        - Salary budgets, 1970 and undated (Box 35)
    - International
      - 1965
        - International operations (Box 35)
    - Los Angeles
      - 1962
        - General, 1962 and undated (Box 35)
    - San Francisco
      - 1962
        - General, 1962-1963 and undated (Box 35)
      - 1965
        - General, 1965 and undated (Box 35)
      - 1966
        - General, 1966 and undated (Box 35)
      - 1967
        - General, 1967 and undated (Box 35)
      - 1968
        - General, 1968 and undated (Box 35)
      - 1969
        - General, 1969-1970 and undated (Box 35)
    - Washington, D. C.
      - 1970
        - General, 1963-1970 and undated (Box 35)
  - Review Board Subseries, 1953-1955 and undated (Restricted)
    Contains meeting minutes, account summaries, correspondence, and Devine's personal notes pertaining to Review Board meetings. The minutes generally include a list of the Review Board members on the client account, the purpose of the meeting, marketing information, analysis of the advertising campaign, and recommendations and conclusions for the client. To maintain quality control, the Review Board assessed individual campaigns at specified intervals with client representatives to ascertain the effectiveness of the campaign and negotiate any changes to the client's advertising program. Account representatives, senior creative staff, and selected management members served on a Review Board for an individual client. The bulk of the Review Board materials found in this collection are not contained in J. Walter Thompson Co. Archives: Review Board Records, 1947 and 1953-1976. Arranged alphabetically by client.
    Conditions Governing Access note
    RESTRICTED: Photocopying from the Review Board Records is prohibited. For further information, consult a reference archivist.
    - Ballantine, 1953-1955 and undated (Box 36)
    - Florida Citrus Commission, 1953-1955 and undated (Box 36)
    - National Broadcasting Company, 1953 and undated (Box 36)
    - Penick and Ford, Ltd., Inc., 1954 and undated (Box 36)
    - Radio Corporation of America, 1953 and undated (Box 36)
- Personnel Series, 1955-1971, and undated (Restricted)
  Comprises correspondence, memoranda, charts, tables, and notes relating to applicants and current, and former JWT employees. Most materials relate to routine business operations such as vacation schedules, job position changes, and salary increase requests, but some describe individual job performance, employment severance, and employee loans. Arranged chronologically.
  RESTRICTED: This series are closed to non-JWT employees for 75 years after 1971, the latest established date in the series. Current JWT employees may view these materials.
  - 1955 (Box 37)
  - 1956, 1956 and undated, 2 folders (Box 37)
  - 1957, 1957 and undated (Box 37)
  - 1958, 1958 and undated (Box 37)
  - 1961, 1961 and undated (Box 37)
  - 1962, 1962-1963 and undated (Box 37)
  - 1971, 1971 and undated (Box 37)
- Oversize Materials
  - Radio/Television Department Series, 1955-1962 and undated
    - Administrative Subseries
      - Department Organization, 1956 and undated
        - Architectural renderings (Oversize-folder 1)
          - Hollywood office, 1956 Feb. 15 (Oversize-folder 1)
          - Los Angeles office, 1956 Feb. 15 (Oversize-folder 1)
          - New York office 12th floor North wing, 1956 Jan. 11 (Oversize-folder 1)
        - Handwritten charts of Radio/Television Department organization (3) and group responsibilities (Oversize-folder 1)
      - House advertising on television, 1957
        - House ads depicting TV Workshop, Kraft Television Theatre, and JWT client shows for 1957 (Oversize-folder 1)
    - Client Subseries, 1955-1962 and undated
      - 1955
        - Ballantine, Map of eastern United States with annotations (Oversize-folder 1)
      - 1957
        - Ford Motor Company
          - Project X: The car that went around the world(1958 Ford) (Oversize-folder 2)
          - Suspicion episode advertisements
            - Diary for Death, undated, 2 advertisements (Oversize-folder 2)
            - Four O'Clock, produced by Alfred Hitchcock, 1957 Sept. 30 (Oversize-folder 2)
        - Joseph Schlitz Brewing Company
          - Schlitz TV News, Vol. 2, No. 3, October 1957 (Oversize-folder 2)
        - Lever Brothers Company
          - The Lux Show Starring Rosemary Clooney, (1957 advertising plans), undated (Oversize-folder 2)
          - Lux Video Theatre
            - Advertisement for A Place in the Sun with Ronald Reagan as host, 1954 Jan. 28 (Oversize-folder 2)
            - Promotional photo of Reagan, undated (Oversize-folder 2)
      - 1958
        - Ford Motor Company